In this video, we're talking about oral
testosterone replacement therapy and
back with us as a guest is Dr. Cash.
Some people call me. Welcome back. Hey,
thanks. Um
yeah, so oral testosterone um it's
it's really one of those things that uh
you know, I think you have to look at
the history of it as well because
it's really a
um
it's come out basically in two different
categories. So, in the past, oral
testosterone was
rightfully so um considered liver toxic.
Um 17 alpha methylation
and uh that means it's going to the
liver, it's getting processed through
the liver, it's toxic to the liver,
and for obvious reasons, it was uh
removed from the market. So, that was
kind of the history of oral testosterone
and that's how some
uh physicians um you know, NPs, PAs, and
current health care professionals tend
to have historically uh viewed oral
testosterone.
What hap- what has happened in previous
years and more more recent years rather
is that uh oral testosterone essentially
got, you know, you could say remade
to be absorbed through the lymphatic
system, you know, specifically through
the gastrointestinal lymphatic system.
And
that's very important because that means
that um now we're able to take a pill
with testosterone in it
that rely that absorbs into your
bloodstream without any liver toxicity.
It's kind of the the bottom line of
oral testosterone.
And so, now we have basically have a new
modality or new method of taking
testosterone.
We have your injections, your topicals.
Obviously, over the years we've had our
pellets and patches and things like that
and you know, that's for a different
video, I think, but uh
um but you know, a pill is a simple
option. It People take pills, various
pills, whether it's their vitamin D,
blood pressure medication, Tylenol,
whatever it is. So,
for it's a it's a new modality, a safe
option of testosterone delivery. So, I
think that's kind of the first key step.
Um
then the next steps come in and that's,
you know, we get into like efficacy, get
into
side effects, you get into, you know,
absorption, comparison to other
modalities. And so,
uh right now we have um you know,
there's been generic uh oral
testosterone undecanoate. That's uh been
on the market and so, here in Canada
um
uh oral testosterone is off the market
for a little bit of time. The generic
came back and then we have Jatenzo and
Kyzatrex. That's uh two brand um
uh
oral testosterone products that are on
the market here,
uh at least in North America.
And so,
um but really uh what these medications
are doing is you're taking, you know,
twice daily testosterone essentially and
uh you're titrating the dose.
You're doing lab monitoring within the
same uh parameters as you would with um
roughly the same as you would with
injections and topicals.
And you're adjusting to, you know,
symptoms essentially. So, I think the uh
a lot of the
you know, on the um practitioner side, a
lot of people
may not have as much experience with
oral testosterone and for a good reason.
I mean, to some extent, it's a
little bit newer com- in comparison to
like injections that have been around
forever, for example, and topicals that
have been around forever.
Um but the a lot of it is really the
same. A lot of what we're doing as far
as monitoring, titration,
adjustments, a lot of it is the same.
And so,
uh
generally, we'll start patients off at a
pretty good dose. We'll have them do
labs in about four or five weeks.
Um the key uh thing with uh oral
testosterone is they should take it with
food in order to make sure there's
optimal absorption and optimal
bioavailability.
And so, that's one area where things can
get a little murky if um patients aren't
taking with food.
And so,
um
we check labs typically about four or
five hours after taking a dose.
So, a bit of a
slight contrast to injections, for
example, where the hours don't really
matter. It's really the days that
matter.
Um but uh for the most part, there's a
lot of room for error though with
checking because uh
there's a there's a bigger range. So, if
a patient checks a little too soon too
late, the levels are relatively stable.
And so,
um we'll typically do monitoring after
about four or five weeks. We'll make an
adjustment. A lot of patients after the
first set of labs will need an upward
dose adjustment typically.
Um we adjust to symptoms a lot,
especially with the
given the lymphatic absorption. I find
that um
you know, sometimes the serum levels
don't always fully reflect how the
patient feels. And so, the patients a
lot of times, they may feel great.
Um and so,
uh that's from speaking with some other
other physicians that do um prescribe
oral testosterone and is they find that
um they really like to even more so
focus on symptoms than anything else.
So, even more so than you would often do
with injectables.
You look and see what works for that
personal patient and you find the right
dose for them.
Um
there's not as much fine-tuning
involved. Again, as long as they're
taking it with food and they're taking
it, you know, spread out throughout the
day like within a reasonable amount of
time, you're spreading your dose out 10,
12 hours or so,
they're pretty much okay with that. I
mean, it's a pretty simple thing to
take. It's just a matter of remembering
to take the pill.
Um in terms of the like
I guess the reasoning for why we need
another why we need this modality of
treatment. So,
there's going to be patients who don't
want to inject, right? I think we all
run into those patients. They don't want
to inject for various reasons. They're
not comfortable injecting, they're not
able to
get into a clinic, or whatever reason. I
mean, they could be all the way across
the country, who knows, right? They're
not comfortable injecting and there's a
lot of patients who don't do as well
with topicals. Some patients do great
with topicals and they do amazing with
it. Some patients don't. Um that's just
how it is. And even with some of the um
um compounding creams, some of patients
don't do well with it. And then with
creams, obviously, cross uh you know,
transfer risk to others. That's a bit of
a risk. Some people don't want to take
that risk. They have a new baby, so on,
for whatever reason. So, having a pill
option just gives a another thing they
can go for
if they're in a situation where like, I
don't want to inject and
I have a baby. I can't I don't want a
cream on me. So, it gives them an
option. And then for others, when we
talk about what's available, like, hey,
um
you know, uh
you can take a pill, you can do this,
you can do that. There's different
options. Here's kind of the pros and
cons. And they're like, I was I want to
try pill first. I'll try for a couple
months, see how I like it. If I don't
like it, maybe I'll switch to
injections. And I think that's totally
fine. And I think one good thing about
the the pills is it's easy to switch
around to.
So, like I got a patient they want to go
from pills to topicals, easy to do. You
can do the change or shift almost
immediately. You want to switch from
pills to injections, very easy to do.
Very easy to shift around. So, I think
uh
there's a lot of flexibility with it. Um
the main downside, I mean, the two
downsides really is um
one, they can't really forget. They
forget, they're going to get some ups
and downs in their levels, which we all
know is not good. And then two,
like anything else, it might not work
well for some people. Absorption could
be variable. Um
you know, and I think uh my personal
opinion is some patients who may have um
malabsorption issues, if they have
inflammatory bowel disease, they've had
gastrointestinal surgery in the past,
um you know, Crohn's disease, maybe
celiac disease. I mean, it depends.
Like, I don't want to
say any hard facts here, but I think if
someone has issues absorbing for
whatever medical reason through their
gastrointestinal tract, like if they
have they can't absorb vitamins well,
they can't absorb fats well, they've had
bariatric surgery. I mean, there's
various patients like that. And I think
I probably would pause a little bit
before offering that to them as like a
good recommendation. I mean, they can
certainly try it out for a couple months
and see how they feel. And but
uh I think at the same time, I would be
telling them, hey, listen, you're taking
a pill.
We already know that you might not
absorb certain medications that well.
So, just FYI, just in the background,
keep in mind you might have to switch to
something else.
And the monitoring really is the same. I
mean, we'll do labs usually about four
or five weeks with these patients. Um
and uh we're kind of watching the same
things um with again with the a lot of
patients I find we often do need to go
up on their dose after the first set of
labs.
Um I don't see a whole lot of um
erythrocytosis.
You know, I think with injectables,
you're going to see a little bit more of
that spike of the erythrocytosis with
the the EPO stimulation, the bone marrow
stimulation with injectables, just with
that spike that happens. But
uh likewise, I find
I find pills are it's not as um
soft, let's say, on the erythrocytosis
as gels and topicals are.
Uh I really say topicals rather than
gels, but it's not as it's not it's not
as soft on that, but it's kind of a
middle ground.
So,
um
and then uh
don't really see a whole lot in terms of
any immediate side effects. Um, I don't
get any gastrointestinal upset. I don't
see a whole lot don't really see a whole
lot of that. So um, I think that's a
it's an option. That's how I usually
tell patients. Doesn't mean that like
this is what you should take
but it's an option.
What about the cost in comparison to
injections or creams?
Yeah, so the
um
the I would say so here uh and I think
probably similarly in the US. Um, so
injections are generally going to be on
the cheapest side.
And uh
pills will be a little bit on the
pricier side.
I would say as you move from generic to
brand based pills, um the price goes up
a bit and we start getting into the
realm of around compounded cream pricing
territory. Mhm. And so yeah, it's a
little I would say if you're going for
like ideal products when it comes to the
pills, the price is going to be a little
bit on the upper ends.
So that's yeah, it's definitely
important to factor in. Whereas
injections
will be on the lower ends of pricing.
All right. So obviously uh at least here
we'll you know, factor in whether Well,
again, I'll present it as an option to
the patients, but obviously if they have
a drug plan or if they
just want it and don't don't care about
the pricing. But uh yeah, I do I do tell
them ahead of time that the the pricing
for this could be a little bit more on
the upper end.
Pricing for injections is more on the
lower ends.
But then you got your guys that are
like, "I will never ever inject." So
Yeah. Yeah. And you told us that
especially with pills, you focus more on
symptoms like most providers do for
creams and injections as well.
Um, but that the levels um don't get
that high maybe.
Yeah, I find that
what we typically see is that I
talked with many people who also
um most very recently actually in the
last week. I've talked to some people
who uh do quite a bit of pills.
And uh what I find is that
yeah, the levels don't get as high
typically, but we get a lot of patients
who feel great
on you know, again, we go up on the
dose, the levels do climb up a bit. But
it there does seem to be a bit of um
almost like a
plateauing effect to to a small extent.
And so um
the we do get levels in the upper ends
of you know, the normal ranges, but we
patients start feeling better even
before that. And so
um, I think there might be a bit of a
disconnect because of that lymphatic
absorption, there could be a bit of a
disconnect between what we're really
seeing in serum levels and maybe what
we're really getting at the androgen
receptor level. I think there's probably
a bit of a disconnect there and so um
it becomes a just a case of hey, saying
"You feel great? Yeah. Do you want any
changes?" Nope, I feel perfect.
And they acknowledge their level is
let's say good or decent and that's kind
of the yeah, that's um
so we'll titrate up upward in terms of
uh
s- improving their symptoms and getting
them feeling really good. Um, but the
levels don't always get as high as we
would expect. But I think uh
I think the lymphatic absorption just
plays a major role into that. And I
think the and I think that the
at the androgen receptor level, we're
just not seeing the same effect as we
would um
like reflected in the serum levels as we
do with injectables and topicals. Yeah.
That's very interesting, yeah. Yeah.